{"tossups": [{"question": "One character in this novel praises Ernest Oppenheimer after gold is discovered and visits a colony of blind basket weavers. A scene in this novel depicts a man planting sticks with flags in the ground in preparation for Mr. Napoleon to teach agriculture to a village. In this novel, the politician Dubula organizes a bus boycott. One character in this novel writes a manuscript titled \"The Truth About Native (*) Crime\" but is murdered before he can finish it. That character also has a bookshelf dedicated to Abraham Lincoln. The priest Theophilus Msimangu informs this novel\u2019s protagonist that his sister Gertrude is sick in, for 10 points, what novel where Arthur Jarvis is murdered by Stephen Kumalo\u2019s son Absalom, by Alan Paton?", "answer": "Cry, the Beloved Country", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cry, the Beloved Country</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cry, the Beloved Country"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One photo taken of two players from this team in the 1987-88 season depicts the tallest and shortest players in the league at that time, Manute Bol and Muggsy Bogues (\"bowgz\"). One controversy surrounding this team in 2009 featured a player bringing guns into the locker room. That player is (*) Gilbert Arenas. A player on this team was notably snubbed from the All-Star game despite being the Eastern Conference\u2019s third-leading scorer. In 2020, this team traded John Wall to the Houston Rockets for Russell Westbrook. Michael Jordan played a brief stint for, for 10 points, what NBA team that stars Bradley Beal and plays in the nation\u2019s capital?", "answer": "Washington Wizards [accept either underlined part; also accept either underlined part of Baltimore Bullets]", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Washington Wizards</u></b> [accept <b><u>either underlined part</u></b>; also accept either underlined part of Baltimore Bullets]", "acceptable": ["Washington Wizards", "either underlined part"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Aurora B helps correct merotelic and syntelic attachments to these things, ensuring their proper biorientation. These things are organized by SMC proteins like condensin and cohesin. The synaptonemal complex acts as a scaffolding between these things, allowing them to form links called \"chiasmata.\" These things are attached to the spindle apparatus by a protein complex called a (*) \"kinetochore\" that binds to their centromeres. These things line up along an imaginary \"plate\" during metaphase, helping ensure that each mitotic daughter cell gets an equal number. For 10 points, name these tightly bundled complexes of histones and DNA, of which humans have 23 pairs per cell.", "answer": "chromosomes [accept homologous chromosomes; accept sister chromatids; accept kinetochores; accept microtubules before \"SMC\"; accept centromeres before \"condensin\"; prompt on chromatin or DNA]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>chromosomes</u></b> [accept <b><u>homologous chromosomes</u></b>; accept <b><u>sister chromatids</u></b>; accept <b><u>kinetochores</u></b>; accept <b><u>microtubules</u></b> before \"SMC; accept <b><u>centromeres</u></b> before \"condensin; prompt on <u>chromatin</u> or <u>DNA</u>]", "acceptable": ["chromosomes", "homologous chromosomes", "sister chromatids", "kinetochores", "microtubules", "centromeres"], "promptable": ["chromatin", "DNA"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One woman in this book is seduced by Abimelech, the king of Gerar, but escapes by pretending to be her husband\u2019s sister. This book, which is called Bereshit (\"Bear-a-sheet\") in Hebrew, sees a man obtain his twin brother\u2019s birthright by dressing in furs. That man later has a vision of a (*) ladder ascending to heaven, and his son is sold into slavery to Potiphar (\"PAA-tuh-fr\") and later works for the pharoah after predicting a famine. In this biblical book featuring Joseph and Jacob, a man asks \"Am I my brother\u2019s keeper?\" after murdering his brother Abel. For 10 points, name this book featuring Adam and Eve where God created the universe, the first book of the Bible.", "answer": "Book of Genesis [prompt on Bible before \"biblical\"]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Book of Genesis</u></b> [prompt on <u>Bible</u> before \"biblical]", "acceptable": ["Book of Genesis"], "promptable": ["Bible"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Mary Jo White investigated this man\u2019s late-term pardon of Marc Rich. During a hearing, this man asked what the meaning of the word \"is\" is. This man fired members of the White House travel office, possibly a reason for Vince Foster\u2019s suicide. This man was nicknamed \"Comeback Kid,\" and was accused of having an affair with (*) Gennifer Flowers. Janet Reno handled the Waco siege under this man. This man was involved in a scandal about a loan to the McDougals; that scandal is the Whitewater scandal. Kenneth Starr investigated this man\u2019s conduct with Paula Jones and Monica Lewinsky. For 10 points, name this 42nd president, whose wife Hillary ran in 2016.", "answer": "Bill Clinton [or William Jefferson Clinton]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Bill Clinton</u></b> [or <b><u>William Jefferson Clinton</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Bill Clinton", "William Jefferson Clinton"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "ANSWER: Bill Clinton [or William Jefferson Clinton] <History - American, AG>  6. At the end of a novel by this author set in Egdon Heath, Diggory Venn is unable to save Eustacia Vye from drowning. This author of Return of the Native also wrote a novel in which a character\u2019s love interest marries Mr. Phillotson while the title stonemason is tricked into marrying Arabella Donn. In that novel, a character murders two children before hanging himself because \"we are too menny.\" That character is (*) Little Father Time. A novel by this author sees a character who works at Talbothays (\"TAL-bow-thaes\") Dairy kill the horse Prince, and who later gives birth to the illegitimate child Sorrow after being raped by Alec. For 10 points, name this author of Jude the Obscure and Tess of the D'Urbervilles.", "answer": "Thomas Hardy", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Thomas <b><u>Hardy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Thomas Hardy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "It\u2019s not the grand potential, but two of this quantity's natural variables are intensive quantities. This quantity was originally defined graphically in 1873 using entropy and volume as coordinates to represent the state of a substance. This quantity applies to processes such as chemical reactions in an open test tube or plants growing in a garden occurring where pressure is near constant, unlike another quantity named for (*) Helmholtz. According to another definition, this thermodynamic quantity is equal to enthalpy minus temperature times entropy. For 10 points, identify this measure of the amount of usable work available in a system, named after the American scientist who developed it.", "answer": "Gibbs free energy [prompt on G; prompt on free energy or energy]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Gibbs free energy</u></b> [prompt on <u>G</u>; prompt on <u>free energy</u> or <u>energy</u>]", "acceptable": ["Gibbs free energy"], "promptable": ["G", "free energy", "energy"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A decade long unrequited passion for Kamila St\u00f6sslov\u00e1 (\"kah-MEE-lah shtuss-LOW-vah\") led Leo\u0161 Jan\u00e1\u010dek (\"LAYH-osh YAH-nah-check\") to write his second work of this type titled \"Intimate Letters.\" Alban Berg\u2019s lyric suite was written in this genre, which inspired B\u00e9la Bart\u00f3k to write six works of this type, the fourth of which introduced his namesake \"snap.\" Beethoven wrote works in this genre including \"Serioso\" and \"Harp,\" and dedicated three to (*) Count Razumovsky. It\u2019s not the symphony, but works in this genre include \"The Joke\" and \"The Emperor,\" which were written by the father of this genre, Joseph Haydn. For 10 points, name this type of chamber music, written for two violins, a viola, and a cello.", "answer": "string quartet", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>string quartet</u></b>", "acceptable": ["string quartet"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this state, Michelle Fischbach defeated Collin Peterson, a member of the Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party. The first Muslim-American elected to Congress, Keith Ellison, serves as Attorney General of this state. A sculpture created by Jordan Powell-Karis depicts a raised fist and was put up at a memorial in this state. A man in this state was killed after using a (*) counterfeit twenty-dollar bill at Cup Foods. A high-profile trial in this state presided over by Judge Peter Cahill and featured witnesses such as Barry Brodd, Genevieve Hansen, and Darnella Frazier. Daunte Wright was shot in this state\u2019s Brooklyn Center, a suburb of its \"Twin Cities.\" For 10 points, name this state where the trial of Derek Chauvin took place for the murder of George Floyd in Minneapolis.", "answer": "Minnesota", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Minnesota</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Minnesota"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Yang-Mills theory about a gap named for this quantity states that all quantum particles have a positive value for it even though they travel at the speed of light. Luminosity is directly proportional to this quantity raised to the 3.5th power. The no-hair theorem states that all black holes can be categorized by charge, (*) angular momentum, and this quantity. The relativistic form of this quantity is determined by the total energy in a system divided by the speed of light squared. Newton\u2019s Second Law states that force equals this quantity times acceleration. For 10 points, name this quantity distinct from weight and usually measured in grams.", "answer": "Mass [do NOT accept or prompt on \"weight\"]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mass</u></b> [do NOT accept or prompt on \"weight\"]", "acceptable": ["Mass"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During this dynasty, Qin Hui (\"CHING hway\") betrayed Yue Fei (\"YWEH fay\") which led to his execution, and Along the River was painted during the Qingming Festival. The Jingkang (\"ZHING kong\") incident occurred during this dynasty, which saw Sima Guang (\"see-muh gwang\") oppose civil service exams introduced by Wang Anshi (\"WONG ahn-shuh\"). This dynasty\u2019s navy was destroyed at the Battle of Yamen. After being captured by Jurchens, this dynasty\u2019s capital moved from (*) Kaifeng (\"KYE-fung\") to Hangzhou (\"hahng-joe\"). This dynasty which invented the compass, movable type, and gunpowder was later taken by the Mongols. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty that was succeeded by the Yuan (\"YOU-WAN\") and lasted between 960 and 1279.", "answer": "Song Dynasty", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Song Dynasty</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Song Dynasty"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "ANSWER: Song Dynasty <History - Other, AL>  12. Controversy surrounding this author of the autobiography Blackberry Winter was dismissed by James E. C\u00f4t\u00e9 as \"Much ado about nothing.\" That controversy arose from the Making and Unmaking of an Anthropological Myth promoted by this author. This thinker studied the Arapesh, Mundugumor, and Tchambuli (\"CHAM-boo-lay\") groups, and their conversations with James Baldwin were recorded in A Rap on Race. This thinker\u2019s most famous work was dismissed by (*) Derek Freeman as her \"Fateful hoaxing,\" and discussed how adolescence was easier on the Pacific island of Ta\u2019u (\"TAH you\") compared to the United States because of the lack of cultural taboos around sexuality. For 10 points, name this anthropologist who studied under Franz Boas, the author of Coming of Age in Samoa.", "answer": "Margaret Mead", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "Margaret <b><u>Mead</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Margaret Mead"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This country is home to the opal capital of the world, Coober Peddy, which lies next to its largest lake, Lake Eyre. A series of fences were erected in this country\u2019s west near the city of Broome to keep out rabbits. This country\u2019s longest river is the Murray-Darling, and the Circular Quay Port borders this country\u2019s largest city. This country\u2019s tallest peak, Mount (*) Kosciuszko (\"KOSS-ee-US-koh\") is located in its Great Dividing Range. Its city of Alice Springs borders a large monolith, Uluru. This country is home to the Torres Strait Islanders and Aborigines. For 10 points, name this country with cities such as Canberra, Melbourne, and Sydney.", "answer": "Commonwealth of Australia", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Commonwealth of Australia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Commonwealth of Australia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This modern-day country\u2019s government subsidized gold exports at extremely high rates during the Goldenberg scandal. In this country, which instituted the colonial kipande system, the White Highlands were reserved purely for European settlers. The first president of this country coined the term \"Harambee\" for community unification and was later tried as part of the Kapenguria Six while taking part in an uprising led by Dedan Kimathi, the (*) Mau Mau Rebellion. This country, whose namesake mountain is the second tallest in Africa, saw Daniel Arap Moi as its second president. For 10 points, name this East African country with its capital at Nairobi, whose first president was Jomo Kenyatta.", "answer": "Republic of Kenya", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Republic of <b><u>Kenya</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Kenya"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One character in this play says that he is possessed by a \"Demon of Experiment.\" That character places a \"vile\" pale blue envelope of money in a dress shop before attempting to seduce Amalia\u2019s daughter. The dress shop in this play is owned by a character who enters when hats and coats are hung on pegs, that character is Madame (*) Pace (\"pah-CHAY\"). This play ends with a mute boy shooting himself and a child drowning in a fountain, after which the Manager complains about having lost a full day of rehearsals. For 10 points, name this absurdist play in which the title family asks to be written about, by Luigi Pirandello.", "answer": "Six Characters in Search of an Author", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Six Characters in Search of an Author</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Six Characters in Search of an Author"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "NOTE TO MODERATOR: Emphasize \"single-runway\" in the second sentence. This city's baseball stadium holds a plaque where the first letter of every word says to \"boycott\" the sponsor of the ballpark. This city houses the busiest single-runway airport, which was formerly known as Lindbergh Field. This city's Imperial Beach is split from the main part of this city by Chula Vista and National City. Torrey Pines has a famous golf course near this city's suburb of (*) La Jolla (\"hoy-yuh\"). Coronado Island is connected by its namesake bridge to this city. The USS Midway Museum can be found in this city, and Balboa Park is located near this city's zoo, famous for its giant pandas. For 10 points, what Southern Californian city is across the border from Tijuana?", "answer": "San Diego, California", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>San Diego, California</u></b>", "acceptable": ["San Diego, California"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "French mathematician Fran\u00e7ois Vi\u00e8te (\"FRANZ-wah Vee-IT\") showed that the solution of many algebraic equations could be expressed using a term added to this function of a number, multiplied by i. The magnitude of the cross product of two vectors equals the product of their magnitudes times this function of the angle between them. The reciprocal of this function is the (*) cosecant, and this function is positive when an angle is in the first or second quadrants. This trigonometric function is often defined as the y-coordinate of a point on the unit circle. For 10 points, name this function which in a right triangle is equal to opposite over the hypotenuse.", "answer": "sine", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>sine</u></b>", "acceptable": ["sine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Another character in this play walks outside on his 60th birthday, and after doing so, lies that he was almost hit by a car. This play, which features the Boer war veterans Wetjoen and Cecil Lewis, sees Margie and Pearl referred to as \"tarts\" by Rocky, who refuses to acknowledge that he is a pimp. In this play, a man who turns his mother in \"out of hatred\" is convinced to commit suicide by a character who calls himself \"The Old (*) Foolosopher\" and jumps off a fire escape. Those two characters are Don Parritt and Larry Slade. For 10 points, what play that sees characters told to abandon their \"pipe dreams\" is set in Harry Hope\u2019s saloon and written by Eugene O\u2019Neill?", "answer": "\"The Iceman Cometh\"", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\"The Iceman Cometh\"</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\"The Iceman Cometh\""], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This artist of a portrait of Margaret Kemble Gage depicted a large Union Jack flag flying above the title figure in his painting The Death of Major Peirson. This painter of Death of the Earl of Chatham and The Siege and Relief of Gibraltar depicted his half-brother Henry Pelham wearing a pink collar and sitting at a wood table with a water glass while holding the title pet with a gold chain in (*) Boy With a Flying Squirrel. This artist\u2019s most famous work was inspired by the sculpture The Borghese Gladiator and sees Morro Castle in the background. In that painting, the title figure lies naked in the water while a harpooner tries to kill the title predator. For 10 points, name this American painter of Watson and the Shark.", "answer": "John Singleton Copley", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Singleton Copley</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Singleton Copley"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Two Thousand Words Manifesto was written during this event. An attempt to deal with this event caused Albania to withdraw from the Warsaw Pact. The end of this event prompted the self-immolation of Jan Palach (\"yan pah-LAH\"). This event\u2019s end saw a period of (*) \"normalization\" led by Gustav Husak (\"WHO-sa\"), undoing reforms of the \"Action Program.\" During this event, the \"socialism with a human face\" program was led by Alexander Dubcek (\"dubh-check\") before a Soviet invasion. For 10 points, name this period of liberalization lasting through 1968, launched in the capital of Czechoslovakia.", "answer": "the Prague Spring", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the Prague Spring</u></b>", "acceptable": ["the Prague Spring"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}